#大家好 現在隔壁老王家的杮子快熟啦
Hi everyone! Now my neighbour, Wang's persimmons are almost ready.
#我跟他說了一下
I've already talked with him.
#搞點來吃一下 就在那邊
We'll pick some for ourselves. They're just over there.
#現在都被樹檔住啦 看不到
We can't see them here as the trees are blocking the sight.
#啊 這裡那麼多草
Ah! Here's so much grass!
#老王肯定10多年都沒有 沒有來過啦
I am sure that Wang hasn't, hasn't stepped onto this place for more than a decade.
#還好意思說是他家的
How cheeky he is to say that it is his place.
#嗯 路都沒有的 全是草
Um, the path has disappeared, covered by grass.
#鳴哇~
Wu wa!
#哇
Wa!
#那麼深的溝
What a deep ditch!
#路都沒有啦
I can't even see the path.
#摘野果都 沒那麼 沒那麼多草
There's even more, more grass than picking wild fruits.
#是喲 這裡怎麼那麼多草
No kidding! How come is here so much grass?
#哇 這有路
Wa! Here's a path,
#找到了原來的路
the original path.
#但是還是很多樹枝
But there are still many branches.
#就沒有 就幾個
Nothing, except a few.
#嗯 這一個黃的
Um! Here's a yellow one.
#哎呀
Aya!
#額 沒份啦 都被鳥吃的
Eh! Nothing for me. It's eaten by birds.
#吃成這樣子的 我都沒
It's already a piece of mess. I'm not,
#無從下口啊
I can't even have a bite.
#不要啦
Pass
#那裡有一個
There's one.
#哇 這個硬邦邦的
Wa! This is as hard as stone.
#你看
Look!
#你看 這黃了哦
Look! It becomes yellow.
#這麼硬 那個鳥都被啄了兩下
It has already been perked by birds though it's still that hard.
#摘了一個
So now I have one.
#你看 那裡還有一個
Look! There's one more.
#就兩個
Just two!
#隔壁的老王
The neighbour Wang,
#我寧願相信世界上有鬼
I'd rather believe that there are really ghosts,
#也不相信老王那張破嘴
than believing the words from Wang's god damn mouth.
#摘掉去
Got it!
沒啦
That's all!
#就搞了兩個
Just two!
Look! This persimmon,
#你看 這個杮子
#有點黃哦
is a bit yellow.
#就搞了兩個 沒啦
So two, that's it!
#有兩個黃的都被鳥吃掉啦
A couple of good ones are already eaten by birds.
#到時候回去 看我們怎麼分
Let's take them back, and see how we can share.
#這一個大 還有一個小哦
A big one and a small one.
#我們兩兄弟分啦 一人一個
Let's share among us, one each.
#拿回去放熟啦 才能吃
They still need to be ripened, before we can eat them.
#老王還騙我們 說一樹都是
Wang is s scam artist. He said that the persimmons are covering the tree.
#騙我幫他開路
He scams my effort to clear the path.
#好啦 我要準備下樹啦
Alright! Let me get ready to get down.
#你看 老王那個騙子 就給我摘了兩個
Look! The scam artist Wang left only two for me,
#只有兩個 一棵樹上只有兩個
just two, just two on the whole tree.
#不是我們摘不到 而是根本沒有
It's not our problem. There's really nothing.
#我去摘野果
I'll pick some wild fruits.
#袋子帶了那麼大 總不能空手回去吧
Getting back home empty-handed with such a large bag is not an option.
#我去摘野果去
I'll pick the wild fruits.
#額 這被鳥吃掉啦
Eh! This has been eaten by birds.
#吃成這樣
Oh man!
#一點都不留給我
They didn't even leave a bit for me.
#那裡有一個 不知摘不摘得到
There's one. Let me see if I can pick it.
#啊 上面一個 不要 太小了那個
Ah! There's one up there. Ah no! It's too small.
#就摘了一個
So just one here.
#摘了一個
I've picked one,
#很黃的
a nice one.
#這個也可以吃的哦 這個是軟的
This is also ready now. It's soft.
#我去看一下有沒有啦
Let's see if there are any more.
#你看 這個都有點黃啦
Look! This is also turning yellow.
#我們再不摘的話 等下就 都被鳥吃掉的
I need to pick it now. Otherwise, it would be eaten by birds.
#要提前把它摘掉
So, pick it now, though a bit early.
#哎喲 這個 那麼緊的
Ayo! It's, so tight.
#刀
Knife?
#不要刀
No
#這個都黃的 看到沒
It's already yellow, see?
#下面都黃啦
The lower part is already yellow.
#很靚
Beautiful!
#看一下其它地方有沒有
Let's see if there are still any at other places.
#樹上有兩個黃的 我上去摘
There are two good ones on the tree. I'll get them.
#不好上
A tough climb.
#哎呀 不只兩個哦
Aya! Not just two.
#不只兩個哦
More than two.
#這麼小
It's so tiny.
#看 跟我的 比我手指大一點點
Look! It's as small, it's just a bit larger than my finger.
#先掰開來看 好不好吃先
Let me crack it open and see if it tastes good.
#嗯 可以喲
Um! Not bad!
#不是很 好小
It's not too, it's tiny,
#但特別好吃
but it's really good.
#這兩個 兩個留給兄弟吃
These two, these two are for my buddies.
#這裡有3個
Here are three.
#啊 被鳥吃啦
Ah! It's eaten by birds,
#吃了一個
one of them.
#這裡還有一個
Here's still one.
#這裡一個
And here too.
#看 這兩個很靚的哦
Look! These two are really beautiful.
#來 把它扔過去
Hey! I'll thrown them to you!
#嗯 這裡有幾個哦
Um! Here're a few.
#有刺
Spikes!
#哇 這個
Wa! This is,
#超級漂亮
super pretty!
#哇 有一隻 裡面有一個
Wa! One, there's one inside.
#這邊也有 但是沒熟
And this side too, but they're not ready.
#不知道有沒有熟 我要嘗一下
I wonder if it's ready. Let me try.
#哇 你看
Wa! Look!
#嗯
Um!
#太好吃啦
Fantastic!
#再嘗一口 沒嘗出味道來
One more bite, to feel better how it tastes.
#嗯 熟啦
Um! It's ready!
#我去看一下裡面還有沒有
Let me see if there are any more inside.
#哇 這裡有一個
Wa! Here's one.
#哇 你看
Wa! Look!
#這個
Isn't it,
#很靚吧
beautiful?
#摘那麼一點點 我要去另外一個地方摘
Just a bit here. Let's continue at other places.
#那 那邊
There, there,
#那邊 就很遠的那邊
somewhere, far far away.
#要把這個路 打開
I need to, clear a path.
#好多刺
Lot of spikes.
#熟是熟啦
The fruits are ready,
#但大部份都被鳥吃掉啦
but most are already eaten by birds.
#這個鳥很壞
The birds are really bad.
#好多刺呀
Lot of spikes!
#你看 就摘了一個
Look! This is the only one,
#像樣一點
which looks not too bad.
#其他都被老鼠跟那個鳥吃掉啦
The rest have already been eaten by mice or birds.
#我現在把它拿回去 到另外一個地方去摘
I'll take it back, and continue at another place.
#到時候等下都沒有啦
Otherwise they'll all be eaten.
#全部沒熟
None is ready.
#青的
All are green.
#你看 今天的勞動成果 (註︰這句充滿社會主義的說話有否一個更有味道的翻譯？)
Look! The reward of today's manual labour.
#就那麼一點點 一下午哇
We spent the whole afternoon, only to have just a bit here.
#這個都軟啦
It's already soft.
#這些都是快黃了的
I've just picked those which are,
#或者黃了的 我就摘啦
turning yellow, or already yellow.
#還有好多青的 沒摘
But there are still a lot of green ones.
#你看這種 這種就是快爛了的
Look! This, this is almost rotten.
#如果不吃掉 也會爛掉的
It would be rotten if I don't eat it now.
#啊 看這個肉
Ah! Have a look at the pulp!
#啊 這味道真的不錯
Ah! The taste is really not bad!
#嗯
Um!
#壞的 這個
It's rotten.
#現在天快黑啦 我要準備回去啦
It's getting dark now. I need to get ready to go back.
#額 太沒勁啦 摘了那麼一點點
Eh, too bad, just a tiny little bit here.
#我過兩天 我過兩天
I'll come again, come again in a couple of days.